<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conformity according to canon justified, and the new way of moderation reproved a sermon preached at Exon, in the cathedral of St. Peter, at the visitation of the Right Reverend Father in God, Anthony by divine permission Lord Bishop of Exon / by William Govld.</title>
            <author>Gould, William, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10196</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13555821</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13555821</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 456:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Conformity according to canon justified, and the new way of moderation reproved a sermon preached at Exon, in the cathedral of St. Peter, at the visitation of the Right Reverend Father in God, Anthony by divine permission Lord Bishop of Exon / by William Govld.</title>
                  <author>Gould, William, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 53 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Maxwell, for R. Royston ..., and are to be sold by Abisha Brocas ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100259:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100259:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Conformity ACCORDING TO CANON JUSTIFIED; AND THE <hi>New Way of Moderation</hi> REPROVED: A SERMON Preached at <hi>EXON,</hi> in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> at the Viſitation of the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Anthony</hi> by Divine permiſſion Lord Biſhop of <hi>EXON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>WILLIAM GO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Maxwell,</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to his moſt Sacred Majeſty, and are to be ſold by <hi>Abiſha Brocas,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Exon.</hi> MDCLXXIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100259:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100259:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in GOD, <hi>Anthony</hi> by Divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend Father in GOD, and my ever-Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT were an unpardonable affront to your Lordſhip, to publiſh to the World, that you have laid a command upon me to be thus publique; for I muſt declare that I had not the ſame injunction to Print this Sermon, that I had to Preach it; but it was partly done to gratify the importunity of the Regular Sons, partly to ſtop the mouths of the malicious enemies of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> The one zealouſly pretended it might be ſomeway uſeful to recover, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote that indiſputable Obedience which is due to our Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions; the other cried it down with noiſe, and clamour, and calumnies; which (with men of their Character and Complexion) drowns all the
<pb facs="tcp:100259:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
force of reaſon and demonſtrations (not to mention the moderate Conformiſt who had two impregnable arguments againſt the following Diſcourſe, the preheminence of <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> and the intereſt of <hi>Demetrius.</hi>) But, my Lord, however this Sermon be entertained, I am happy in the opportunity, of thus open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſing my ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>your Lordſhips moſt humble and obedient Servant, <hi>William Gould.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Kenne Devon.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept. 28. 1674.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100259:3"/>
            <head>Conformity according to Juſtified, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 14.40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let all things be done Decently and in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THAT men pretending a tender Conſcience ſhould have <hi>Eſtrich</hi>-ſtomachs, and digeſt Iron rather than Obedience, eſteem a Surplice more criminal than Schiſm, and Sedition leſs culpable than Ceremonies; plead for compaſſion from the weakneſs of their Brains, when they have a ſtubbornneſs in their Necks, which will not bow to any Regular Conſtitutions: This is at once ſo ridiculous and miſchievous an Impiety, as puts all <hi>Hyperboles</hi> to a <hi>nonplus.</hi> Who (but a Refractory Non-conformiſt) One who adheres to his own Concluſion in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100259:4"/>
to all Premiſſes, could ever declare (by his publique practice) That the Whore and the Beaſt are more nearly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied to the Order and <hi>Decorum</hi> of my Text, than Sacriledg to the late thorow godly Reformation, or Witchcraft to Diſobedience? But theſe are not the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſecutors of this beſt of Reformed Churches: We have a ſort of men, who are neither for Liturgy nor Directory, Canon nor Covenant; part Churchmen, and part Schiſmatical; having one Leg for a Tub, and another for a Pulpit, one Hand ſubſcribing to ſeparate Worſhip, and the other to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſuch who conform to the Benefice (not to the Canons) and (Pope-like) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel all their ſolemn Obligations to the Laws, and give themſelves a pardon, and diſpenſation, for their barbarous Irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity againſt the Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: <hi>Ex animo</hi> (in their Subſcription) ſignifies Lukewarmneſs, and Neutrality; an unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent is a deep Hypocriſie; Decently, is a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with a faction, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100259:4"/>
to moderation, and (too frequently) according to contribution.—</p>
            <p>Now we have not the Title of preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soul-ſearching Miniſters, unleſs we ſell Divine Worſhip to accommodate our Intereſts, and add a precious breach of all our promiſes and engagements, to the utmoſt height of all Sacriledg and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs: He is your only Man of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Principles, whoſe Conſcience is a Compoſition of Five precious Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents; the Pride of <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>Demas,</hi> the Treachery of <hi>Judas,</hi> the Hypocriſie of the Phariſees, and the Diſobedience of Devils: Such with whom to pray by the Purſe is to pray by the Spirit, who expoſe to ſale their Duty and the Laws, at the deſpicable penſion of a few Ignorant Zealots, who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Saints before they are Chriſtians, and are Heirs of Heaven without the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility of Heathens, or the Morals of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels; Theſe are your bleſſed Epiſcopal Covenanters, Canonical Comprehenders, Clergy Merchants, and Regular Renega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, whoſe very Character is Nonſence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100259:5"/>
and Contradictions: It is from their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devotion, Irreverence and wilful Omiſſions (as if ſome offenſive vapours did aſcend from our excellent Devotions) that the people ſeldom enter ſome of our Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, till the Air be firſt purged, and cleanſed, and made clear and free to breath in by the Raviſhing Meeter of <hi>Sternhold</hi> and <hi>Hopkins.</hi> Theſe are your powerful men of God, deſcribed by <hi>Tertullian</hi> of old,<note place="margin">Tert. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi. ſcript. cont. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note> 
               <hi>Qui ſimplicitatem volunt eſſe proſtrationem diſciplinae, cujus apud alios curam lenocinium vocant</hi>— The Church hath a Cuſtom to preſcribe the Laws of Order, relating to Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and theſe have a Cuſtom that they be not obſerved. Their Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the overthrow of Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Goverment, and their Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is a wilful Omiſſion of the Rites and Offices of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> It is with theſe men (as with <hi>Servilius</hi> in <hi>Rome) Medium ſe gerendo nec plebis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit odium, nec apud patres gratiam iniit.</hi> Thus theſe pleaſe neither the Church nor the Schiſmatick;— not the Laſt (becauſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100259:5"/>
not wholly Irregular) nor do they act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Canonical Precepts of their Mother, becauſe all things are not <hi>done decently and in order. Calvin</hi> (who with ſome is of more Authority than all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) calls the Text the Canon of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, giving life and efficacy to all our Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions.— <hi>Regula eſt ad quam omnia quae ad externam Eccleſiae Politiam ſpectant exigere convenit.</hi> The Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> obſerves, That upon theſe Two all Uniformity is built, rendring the firſt—according to Cuſtom, (Cuſtom being the Rule of Decency) and the other words according to Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>(viz.)</hi> of the Governours of the Church of God: The Learned Bp. <hi>Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> (on <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5.) (where we have the ſame word for order as in the Text) tells us, It is a Military Term, implying the Church is a well Marſhal'd Camp, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſtricteſt Diſcipline is obſerved and exerciſed; It is <hi>an Army with Banners (Cant.</hi> 6.9.) and ſo where this requiſite Order of Offices, Diſtinctions, Ranks, and Files, and Poſtures are not obſerved
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100259:6"/>
(it's in an Army of Souldiers) <hi>non Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtica Diſciplina ſed politia Cyclopica eſt,</hi> ſaith the Reverend Prelate, upon that Text. The Church then is not all Head, nor all Body; no Roman Monarchy, nor Diſciplinarian party; no Familiſtical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, nor Anabaptiſtical Anarchy; but a well-compacted Army of Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, who have liſted themſelves by their Baptiſmal Covenant to live and dye Chriſts faithful Souldiers, and under the Banner of the Croſs, to follow the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of their Salvation, the Eternal Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. The Lord-Marſhals under this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious General, are the Sovereign Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes; and in the next degree of Eminence, the Reverend Fathers, and Paſtors of the Church, who are eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to provide that the God of the Armies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> be ſolemnly worſhipped in the beauty of holineſs; and that the Rules of Order be obſerved by all the Inferiour Officers of the Church in their ſeveral ſtations— <hi>Hic Ergo quae conducant leges tantum abeſt ut damnemus, ut his ablatis, diſſolvi ſuis nervis Eccleſias totasque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formari,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100259:6"/>
ac diſſipari contendamus:</hi> So <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> in the Tenth Chapter of the Fourth Book of Inſtitutions. Order and Decency are the hedges fencing the ſubſtance of Religion from all the Indignities of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledg and Prophaneneſs; as the glorious <hi>Laud</hi> ſpake quaintly and piouſly, who became formidable to the Roman Intereſt, by purſuing the External <hi>Decorum</hi> of my Text in the Engliſh Church.</p>
            <p>The general Concluſion (according to moſt Expoſitors upon this Text) is briefly this.</p>
            <p>There is a Power in Eccleſiaſtical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, to make Laws, and Canons, and to decree Rites of Order and <hi>Decorum,</hi> for the External Solemnization of Divine Service, to which all under their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Prieſts, and People are obliged to yield a regular and a conſcientious Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Which I ſhall briefly and very plainly demonſtrate by Scripture, Reaſon and Experience, Fathers, Councils, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, and the Confeſſion of Adverſaries, and ſo make Application to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100259:7"/>As to the firſt, I humbly offer Six un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Scripture-Principles, which this Reverend Audience is able to defend againſt the moſt Learned and Judicious Nonconformiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Apoſtles intended Unity (as in the known Chapter of Unity the Fourth to the <hi>Epheſians</hi>) and to preſerve Unity, they recommend Order and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Church of Chriſt, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears ſufficiently from <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.6. compared with <hi>Coloſſians</hi> 2.5. and this Canon of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Apoſtles (at the firſt Preaching of the Goſpel) did not eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh that Order, which the State of the Church did afterwards require. <hi>The reſt will I ſet in order when I come,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. Upon which words the Aſſembly of Divines are as politiquely reſerved and ſilent, as in the caſe of Sacriledg in their Annotations, <hi>ad</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>pertinet</hi> (ſo <hi>Grotius) ad ordinem pertinet Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> (ſo <hi>Pareus) Certum eſt</hi> Paulum <hi>non niſi de externo decoro loqui</hi> (ſaith <hi>Calvin) quod ut in Eccleſiae libertate poſitum eſt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100259:7"/>
ita pro temporum, locorum, hominum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione, conſtitui debet</hi>— The Second Scripture-principle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> The Apoſtles expected ſuch a Setlement to be made by thoſe to whom they entruſted the Government of the Church: <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in Creet, to ſet in order the things that are wanting,</hi> or (as the Original) <hi>left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, Titus</hi> 1.5. Upon which <hi>Walo Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalinus,</hi> or <hi>Salmaſius</hi> (he who called the bleſſed Dr. <hi>Hammond, Nebulo,</hi> for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of Biſhops) he himſelf does ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, That <hi>Titus</hi> had an Epiſcopal Power, at leaſt in the Judgment of all the Greek Fathers; particularly quoting St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Theodoret, Theophilact</hi> and others: (To ſet in Order the things that are wanting,) <hi>quae ego ob brevitatem tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris &amp; impedimenta a Cuſtodibus ordinare non potui:</hi> (So <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Grotius.</hi>) Hence two things are very naturally and genuinely deducible.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That St. <hi>Paul</hi> (as to External Order, for he omitted no Eſſentials) had left ſome things undone in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100259:8"/>
Church in his own Judgment fit to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards (at <hi>Creet</hi>) eſtabliſhed: <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> He committed the accompliſhment of theſe Externals, relating to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Decency of the Church to the (at leaſt) Epiſcopal, ſome ſay Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal, <hi>Titus,</hi> as having under him many Biſhops; which is the Third Scripture-principle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Apoſtles gave certain Canons to direct Church-Governours in in ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Eſtabliſhments, to preſcribe ſuch things, which (according to the conditions of times and places) ſhould ſeem moſt expedient to Order, Honeſty, Edification, and Peace; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31, 32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27, 29. and the precept of the Text. Hence <hi>Calvin</hi> ſoundly teacheth (his too credulous Proſelytes in deeper Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) that ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and Canons, are not to be eſteemed as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Traditions, <hi>quia fundatae ſunt in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerali lege, Omnia decenter, &amp;c.</hi> Whence in his Inſtitutions <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines concerning kneeling at publick
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100259:8"/>
Prayers in obedience to ſuch Church-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, to be a Divine as well as Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Inſtitution; Divine, as founded in the general Precept, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order:</hi> And Human, as framed by Governours according to that general Injunction of the Apoſtl's: Hence <hi>Beza (in Confeſſione fidei; cap.</hi> 5.) all ſuch Laws as to their end and foundation, <hi>ſunt Divinae &amp; Coeleſtes:</hi> Which is the fourth Principle of the holy Oracles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Apoſtles gave only gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules, and ſo ſuppoſed a Power in the Governours to frame thence particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Rites, conſonant with their general Canons. Thence <hi>Calvin, non poteſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri quod</hi> Paulus <hi>hic exigit niſi additis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervationibus, tanquam vinculis quibus ordo ſervetur.</hi> But more plainly <hi>Pareus, facit Eccleſiae poteſtatem de ordine &amp; deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro Eccleſiaſtico liberis diſponendi &amp; ferendi leges:</hi> The only queſtion is, Where this Power was placed? (for at this time Kings were not nurſing Fathers to the Church;) <hi>for this cauſe left I thee to ſet in order,</hi> as before expreſt, it was lodged in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100259:9"/>
the Biſhops, and Governours of the Church by the bleſſed Apoſtles—which is the fifth Principle conſonant with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Oracles.</p>
            <p>Laſtly (the Five former Principles ſuppoſed) That we ought to obey ſuch orderly Canons is included under <hi>obedite praepoſitis, Heb.</hi> 13.17. There are two words in that Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Obey and ſubmit your ſelves;</hi> The one relating to active and the other to paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. If Church-Governours do give out Precepts and Directions for the Policy of the Church, or the <hi>Decorum,</hi> or Order of Divine Service, here <hi>obedite praepoſitis</hi> takes place according to the former Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and there is a paſſive Subjection due (called Submiſſion by the Caſuiſts) where we cannot pay the other active O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, but in doubtful Caſes, <hi>praeſumptio eſt pro Autoritate imponentis,</hi> ſay Divines. And ſo much briefly for Scripture-Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Light of Nature and right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth apologize for this Power in our Eccleſiaſtical Superiours: This Topique
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100259:9"/>
(to the great advantage of the cauſe) Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> in his <hi>Irenicum,</hi> Book the firſt, the third, fourth, fifth, and ſixth Chapters) hath taken out of my hands: He there proves, that the Light of</p>
            <p n="1">1. Nature dictates that there be a Society for the worſhip of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this Church-ſociety be govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a decent and orderly manner.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That there be a Diſtinction of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and a Superiority of Powers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Governours be reverenced according to their Employments and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Obedience paid to their ſolemn Conſtitutions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, That every offender do give an account of his actions to ſuch Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and ſubmit to their Cenſures: So far Nature goes, as that learned Man fully demonſtrates which is ſufficient as to the Second Particular, referring thither (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I cannot add, and will not diminiſh) all that are curious of ſatisfaction in the Caſe before us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When we exchanged a <hi>Charles</hi> for an <hi>Oliver,</hi> a Biſhop for a Lay-elder,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100259:10"/>
the Oaths of Allegiance and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Obedience for Covenants and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, and a Liturgy for a Directory, you know the Conſequence, by a ſad and dear-bought experience; no ſooner were Order and Decency removed from the holy Oratories, no ſooner were Prieſts and People indulged to their own fancies and conceptions in Preaching, Hearing, Adminiſtration and Reception of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and Publick Prayers, but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately we had Pulpit againſt Pulpit, Altar againſt Altar, Preaching and Prayer, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as <hi>Antipodes,</hi> Ordinance juſtling out Ordinance, (that to ſpeak with <hi>Eraſmus) ingenioſa res fuit eſſe Chriſtianos.</hi> Such who never ſate at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> ſtept up into the Chair of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the People were taught from the mouth of a Cannon, and the Church ſwept with the Beſom of Deſtruction: The Weaver be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came inſpired, and had new Lights and glorious Diſcoveries, the Mechanical <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius,</hi> a precious diſpencer of the Words and Sacraments; and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Copperſmith could challeng the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100259:10"/>
Aſſemblies at Gifts and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. The Souldier undertook to cut the Text, and could as powerfully Preach Swords, and Pray Granadoes, and as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly curſe <hi>Meroz,</hi> as any of our Soul-ſearching Miniſters, who firſt pulled down King and Biſhops by the form of Godlineſs, and the Vertue of <hi>Hocus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus:</hi> (That there might be no want of Labourers) The Common-Reaper thruſt his Sickle into the Lords Harveſt, and Common Shepherds qualified themſelves for the overſight of the Flock of Chriſt, and the Cloak and Apron Preach'd down Gowns and Univerſities; and he whoſe occupation it was to mend the old Shoes of the Prophets, had the poſſeſſion of Desk and Pulpits, Venting Treaſon, Nonſence and Blaſphemy by the Hour-glaſs; we had a <hi>New-England</hi> Medley inſtead of <hi>Decorum</hi> and Reverence, and an <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> hotch-potch (as many Religions as <hi>Babel</hi> had Languages:) inſtead of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and the Beauty of Holineſs, we began to number Articles of Religion almoſt by the Million (as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100259:11"/>
ſaid of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi>) The <hi>Chariſma</hi> of boldneſs acted the part of the Gift given by Impoſition of hands; and he that could neither Write nor Read (by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Lungs and Impudence) was taught to pray <hi>Extempore</hi> in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Saints: A Phrenzy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came deſirable for its Lucid intervals, and it was thought a glorious attainment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others to be beſides our ſelves; our Churches were Gariſons to keep out the Sacrifice of Obedience, and its Notaries, while by prophane boldneſs, pious Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and tumultuary Effuſions, men day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered unto God the Sacrifice of Fools: We had Stones given us inſtead of Bread, and amidſt perpetual holding forth, ſuffered a Famine of the Word, and by all men (not diſtracted) Divines and Preachers, Scholars and ſuch as car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on the Work, were very carefully diſtinguiſhed, ſome <hi>Oxford</hi>-Schiſmatick petitioned the pretended Parliament, to ſend down Miniſters to teach the Colledg-Graduates (how to Preach down Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Sciences, I ſuppoſe) under the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100259:11"/>
pretence that they ſtood in need of more powerful Inſtructers: The progeny of Sects grew too Numerous for any other way of Arithmetick than the Stars of Heaven, or Sands by the Sea-ſhore for multitude; the Queſtions of our Creed almoſt as Numerous as the Letters of it; ſuch who boaſted Communion with Chriſt in the pureſt Ordinances of Worſhip, baniſhed his Prayer from the Pulpit, and imputed Blaſphemy and Atheiſm to the glorious Form of the Saviour of the World: The Ark of God was a kind of <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark with us, where the unclean Beaſts were herded up together without order or diſtinction, and the Church (our Mother) once the joy of the whole Earth, equally overwhelmed with grief and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. <hi>We found her in the Wood</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of the Ark of Divine ſervice) ſtript of all her due Attendants and Solemnities, and the Cathedrals turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Stables: Where the Sacriledg had ſome ingenuity, To give ſo lively an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the vaſt difference between <hi>Laud,</hi> the Glorious, and the new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100259:12"/>
of this beſt of Reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Tell me now, ye prudential Clergy-men (whoſe Moderation is a conſtant omiſſion of the holy Rites and Offices of the Church) does not the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms experience proclaim a Zeal for our Canons to be a Zeal according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg? Is it not the Policy and temporal Intereſt of a Prieſt (aſwell as his indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpencible Duty) to obey our orderly Conſtitutions? Thou (High and Mighty Maſter of the Politicks) When was thy Mother the Eye and Glory of all the Chriſtian Churches? Was it not when the Ark was ſetled with a Decent Splendour amongſt us? When the Eccleſiaſtical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchy enjoyed its full Authority and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements? When the venerable Courts of Juſtice dazled the eyes and brake the hearts of the moſt inſolent of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders? And all the parts of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice performed with that <hi>Decorum</hi> as is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the Canon of the Text (with a ſolemn Reverence). Since theſe things are ſo by experience, lay then aſide, (my moderate Brother) this Lukewarm kind
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100259:12"/>
of Temper; ſet a higher eſtimate on the Churches Peace and Honour, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to her recovery (to ſome degrees at leaſt) of the ancient Luſtre, <hi>By doing all things decently and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Ancient Fathers and Councils joyn with Scripture, Reaſon, and Experience, as to this Power (by me pleaded for from the Text) in our Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſiaſtical Superiors. Thus St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to <hi>Caſulanus,</hi>— in things undetermined in the Word, <hi>Mos populi, Dei, &amp; inſtituta majorum, pro lege Dei tenenda ſunt:</hi> Hence St. <hi>Bernard (Epiſt.</hi> 7.) of things abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely good or abſolutely evil, the Caſe is Evident; the one muſt be not done when commanded, the other done though prohibited by Superiors; <hi>inter haec ſunt media quaedam, in his fas non eſt ſenſum noſtrum ſententiae praeſcribere Magiſtrorum.</hi> To both aſſents the old <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Book <hi>De corona Militis,</hi> where ſpeaking of kneeling, the ſign of the Croſs, of ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Prayers between <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide,</hi> and many other Rites and Cuſtoms of the Primitive Church, <hi>Harum &amp; alia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100259:13"/>
ejuſmodi diſciplinarum, ſi legem expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtules Scripturarum, nullam invenies, &amp;c.</hi> Hence thus much is clear from Antiquity, that the Ancient Chriſtians of the pureſt Ages of the Church were not in bondage to a Scruple, nor ſtartled at a Ceremony, nor ever ſaid to their Governours, ſhew us a Text for ſuch Rites and Orders; They too well underſtood Chriſtian Liberty and themſelves, to throw away their Time, Intereſt, Peace, and Safety, for the mere Fringes of the Garment of the body of Religion with our peeviſh, and (withal obſtinate) Renegadoes: That condition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Aſſent and cautionary (though not) abſolute Obedience we do owe to our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Paſtors and Governors (albeit we have not expreſs Commiſſion out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the very particulars) cannot be denied by any Man in his ſenſes; for to diſpute in ſuch a Caſe, inſtead of yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Obedience, is to declare to the World, that when Chriſt aſcended up on high, his Donation of ſpiritual Authority was a Donation of Titles without Reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; whereas he that ſaid, <hi>He that reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100259:13"/>
Kings, reſiſteth God, Rom.</hi> 13. The ſame Wiſdom of God (by whom Princes Reign) ſaid alſo, <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me, and he that deſpiſeth you, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth me and him that ſent me.</hi> Theſe are the Prerogatives of ſpiritual Guides, and were never eſteemed words of courſe or formality in the Primitive Church: And the Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius</hi> (an Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Biſhop, vindicated by <hi>Voſſius,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Pearſon,</hi> are an admirable Comment in this Caſe, upon <hi>obedite praepoſitis</hi>—Be ye ſubject to the Biſhop, as unto the Lord; Reverence your Biſhops according unto the precepts of the Apoſtles; he that acts of his own head without the Biſhop is polluted in his Conſcience; attempt nothing in the Church againſt Epiſcopal Conſtitutions, are known expreſſions in the writings of old <hi>Ignatius</hi>— But I intend a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular vindication (under this Topick of Antiquity) of this beſt of Reformed Churches: Firſt, As to her Impoſition of a Liturgy; Secondly, as to the Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of orderly Rites, and Thirdly, a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100259:14"/>
Vindication of the Authority alſo (as Primitive) by which our Canons are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.— Briefly to each of theſe.</p>
            <p>Thus the Fourteenth Canon of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is truely Primitive— <hi>The Miniſter ſhall uſe the preſcribed Forms and Rites in the Common-Prayer-Book, without diminiſhing in regard of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or any other reſpect, or adding any thing in the matter or form thereof.</hi>—</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Miniſter ſhall uſe the preſcribed Forms and Rites, &amp;c.</hi> Thus, <hi>in Synodo Epnuenſi,</hi> in the Order of the Celebration of Divine Offices, the Metropolitical Church was the Standard for the whole Province, to keep the better <hi>Decorum</hi> in all Sacred Adminiſtrations. And in the Fourth Council of <hi>Toledo,</hi> they declare it conſonant with the ancient Canons of the Church, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t unus ordo orandi &amp; Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendi conſervetur, nec diverſa ſit a nobis Eccleſiaſtica conſuetudo, quia una fide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinemur &amp; Regno;</hi> the ſame Forms, and no other, as the Council of <hi>Africa, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi> 103. The Third Council of <hi>Carthage, Canon</hi> 231. The Council of <hi>Laodicea,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100259:14"/>
Canon</hi> 181. And above all the Council of <hi>Milevis (Canon</hi> 12.) for a ſufficient Reaſon there rendred, <hi>Nec aliae preces niſi quae a Synodo Comprobatae dicerentur in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, ne aliquid contra fidem aut bonos mores per ignorantiam aut minus ſtudium ſit Compoſitum:</hi> So that hence our impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Forms upon Prieſts and People, is clearly juſtiflable from the Practice of the Primitive Churches of Chriſt—It is Recorded of <hi>Proclus</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in his Treatiſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That St. <hi>Baſil</hi> firſt, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> contracted the Liturgy of St. <hi>James,</hi> that upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of mens ſlothfulneſs and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they might not Nauſeate for the length, and ſo Apoſtatize from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Tradition of Liturgies—The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy now aſcribed to St. <hi>James</hi> may be denied on good Reaſons, yet that St. <hi>James</hi> made a Liturgy, the Council of <hi>Trullo</hi> long ſince acknowledged, and is at this day by the <hi>Greek</hi>-Church openly own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and profeſt; and amongſt them to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion it, were the ready way to be laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100259:15"/>
at as eminently ridiculous. The <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deburgenſes</hi> have collected from ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of <hi>Origen,</hi> on <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> That it is without diſpute a doubt, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians had Forms of Prayer in the Third Century.<note place="margin">Scal. lib. 6. 573. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nev. 1629.</note> 
               <hi>Scaliger, de Emendatione tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum,</hi> declares that he had himſelf ſeen an ancient Liturgy of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts (by the way) to one Common Prayer, and to one mind in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Magneſians.</hi> And what elſe means <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> by his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Apol. 2.</note> or <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tert. de oratione.</note> by his <hi>Oratio Legitima &amp; ordinaria;</hi> and by that Form of Praying for the Emperours, <hi>ut illis foret vita pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixa, imperium ſecurum, ſenatus fidelis, Exercitus fortis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apol. 30.</note> 
               <hi>domus tuta, populus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, orbis quietus,</hi> which ſome (not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probably conjecture) to be grounded on St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Charge to <hi>Timothy, That Prayers be made for all, then eſpecially Kings, &amp;c.</hi> making it <hi>Timothy</hi>'s cheif care (as Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus</hi>) rightly to Frame and Order the Publick Prayers of the Church. And what elſe doth St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> intimate <hi>(de Oratione) publica nobis eſt &amp; communis
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100259:15"/>
oratio</hi>— or the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Conſtantine</hi> obſerved with the whole Aſſembly of Chriſtians Recorded by <hi>Euſebius;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebius de vita Conſtanti. in lib. 4. cap. 17. 19</note> So that whether we conſider the uſe of a Liturgy, we are juſtified by the Fathers; or the Impoſition of it on the Clergy, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly with excluſion of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, the Church of <hi>England</hi> herein obſerves the prudence of the Ancient Councils and Synods (long before Popery was introduced) and ſo liable to ſuch trifling exceptions from our Puritan Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>Again Secondly, not to diminiſh (in regard of Preaching) the Prayers of the Church (the Fourteenth Canon Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us) and that the Pulpit ſhould not ſwallow up the Desk, this Auditory is not to be taught, to be the high prudence and politick zeal of the Ancient Churches of Chriſt. You know that <hi>Juſtyn Martyr</hi> ſaith, when the Reader had done, then the Preacher exhorts (in his Apology) you know that in the primitive times (as now) there was a firſt and a ſecond Service, the one preceeded, the other followed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100259:16"/>
the Sermons or Homilies; and ſo Preaching and Prayer did not ſhoulder out one another, but walked hand in hand as friends, and not as <hi>Antipodes</hi> in the holy Oratories. The Sermons anciently came in, <hi>poſt recitationem Evangelii, after the rehearſal of the Goſpel,</hi> being uſually a Diſcourſe upon it; and hence it is an eaſie collection, that Preaching had its due eſteem, yet never ſo magnified as that the Liturgy ſhould be laid aſide to make way for the Sermon. The moſt eminent Preachers (as <hi>Baſil, Chryſoſtom</hi> and others) were Compilers of Liturgies, but could never endure (as is clear by many paſſages in their writings) that the people ſhould throng more to their Diſcourſes, than to the pure Word of God read in the Church in Divine Service, or to the common Devotions— That was no Muſick to the old zealous Saints (the holy Biſhops and Prieſts) which now affords ſuch a mighty pleaſure to men of moderate principles, the croud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of people to a Sermon, and leaving the Church empty and waſt at the ſolemn Prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100259:16"/>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> (Not only not to diminiſh on the account of Preaching;) But alſo in no other reſpect, ſaith the Canon afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, nor to add any thing in the matter or form thereof (a Conſtitution truely Primitive;) for in Ancient times, ever ſince the ceaſing of miraculous Gifts it was never permitted any Presbyters to add to, or detract from the publick preſcribed Service, or to make any private Prayers of their own in the holy Oratories.</p>
            <p>There is no footſtep of Record or Monument in the Church of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our Moderate Clergy can make it probable, that in the ſolemn and ſet Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of Chriſtians conſtantly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, a Presbyter was ever allowed to utter any thing of his own or others compoſing, premeditated or extemporary, without the approbation of his Biſhop firſt had in the matter of Prayer (which we now are diſcourſing of)—It is an impudent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true Aſſertion (I wonder it could ever enter into any Mans mind) that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may of themſelves, curtail or add to the Service preſcribed, or modify the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100259:17"/>
Worſhip of God. But on the contrary (as <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his <hi>Cure of Church-Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> doth well note) no Man queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but ſome Form of Prayer was impoſed on the Jewiſh Miniſters of old, and a Form of Prayer taught the Prieſts, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.17. To which I add, ſince the Word of God hath given us Forms of Worſhip, of Praiſe and Prayer in the Houſe of God; If we will allow the Compoſers of thoſe Forms to be of Gods own appointment (which cannot be denyed), we have in Scripture too, in concurrence with the Ancient Church, found out ſome appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make Prayers for other Paſtors and Churches, to offer up unto God— And we find <hi>Titus</hi> for this purpoſe left in <hi>Creet to ſet in order what was wanting, ad</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (So <hi>Grotius) Pertinet</hi>— and <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> is charged with this Office as Biſhop 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. an Order is there given him touching the ſubſtance of Publick Prayer to be ſetled in the Aſſemblies of his Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, as Maſter <hi>Thorndyke</hi> notes and proves in his Treatiſe, The Service of God in publick Aſſemblies— <hi>in Timotheo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100259:17"/>
mandata dat Epiſcopis,</hi> ſo <hi>Grotius</hi>— Again in the Impoſition of orderly Rites at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on the publick Worſhip, it was the ſtile of old, <hi>Si quis praeſumſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit, ſi quis contumaciter fecerit, Anathema ſit;</hi> which is well Engliſhed in our 34th. Article, by Laws eſtabliſhed, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall (through his private Judgment) openly and wilfully, and purpoſely break the Rites of Decency and Order enjoyned, ſhall be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, &amp;c.</hi> Such therefore who are in profeſſion Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (whoſe Impoſition of a Liturgy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Rites, is thus prudentially primitive and moderate) and do wilfully, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly violate the Orders preſcribed, by robbing God and the People of any parts of the publick Worſhip or Rites thereof, upon the account of Preaching, or the free Prayers of the Pulpit, they do very wickedly. I leave their own Conſciences to condemn them till God himſelf doth; which he will certainly do without a more honeſt and zealous adheſion to the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Conſtitutions. It would be Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly arrogant in me to prove out of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100259:18"/>
Antiquity, that the reading of the Litany, the obſervation of the Feaſts and Faſts, Catechizing, viſiting the Sick, and giving them their <hi>viaticum,</hi> the Croſs in Baptiſm, the Rites of <hi>Decorum,</hi> and the Decent Habits of the Clergy-men, and many other Canons, which this preſent Audience ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently knows to be truely conſonant to the ancient Canons and primitive uſage: But you muſt give me leave to ſay, that theſe are ſo far omitted, not out of a prudential, but ſchiſmatical, Compliance— <hi>Pudet haec opprobria nobis,</hi> is too mild a reproof; (like that of <hi>Eli</hi> to his Sons, <hi>It is no good report, ye make the Lords People tranſgreſs</hi>) Too meek a reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſuch Sons of <hi>Corah</hi> or <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> who by a barbarous diſobedience to the Laws, indeavour to bring into this Church, <hi>tot ſchiſmata, quot Sacerdotes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider we again, under this head of the Fathers and Councils, the Authority confirming the preſent Canons of this Church, and we ſhall find That alſo, by undeniable evidence, equally primitive with the Conſtitutions themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100259:18"/>We have ſuch Canons as are treated on by Biſhops and Prieſts, but they do not (with the <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Conventicle of Divines) meet without the Royal Call and Summons, nor ſit and act when the King Commands their diſſolution (with the <hi>Glaſcow</hi>-Aſſembly of ſpiritual Lay-elders) but we own the Kings Power, <hi>a parte ante,</hi> to convene the Prelates and the Clergy-Repreſentatives, and <hi>a parte poſt,</hi> to oblige their Subjects, by their Confirmation, to a Regular Obedience. A clear primitive Practice, aſſoon as ever God gave Kings to be Nurſing-fathers to the Church (as is admirably proved by <hi>Cauſabon, Grotius, Morney Dupleſſis,</hi> our own <hi>Jewel, Field, Whitaker</hi> and others, beyond all exceptions: Now where King and Biſhops thus joyn in Eccleſiaſtical Laws (according to the conſtant Practice of Chriſts Church) where <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Oaths of Allegiance, and Canonical Obedience meet together to oblige us, there is not now the leaſt pretence for a Man in Orders to deſpiſe ſuch Rules as are truely Primitive in themſelves; when
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100259:19"/>
the Canons are treated on by the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Order, which hath filled our Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars with Saints, our Hiſtories with Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Church with Martyrs; and when this Order is ſubject to Kings, and ſupported by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and both appointed of God for the Management of the Church under the bleſſed Jeſus, he is neither a true Prieſt nor Chriſtian that denies obedience.</p>
            <p>And here I do, with all duty and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, moſt humbly beſeech your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and all (under you) advanced to any Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the truely-regular Clergy in their cheerful ſubmiſſion to the truly ancient Laws and Canons of this beſt of Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches.</p>
            <p>When the Schiſmatick keeps a Faction in pay, and allows Schiſm a Salary, and gives a penſion to the hollow-hearted <hi>Judas</hi> of moderate Principles to break and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide us, 'tis pitty the Zealous Conformiſt ſhould want a Benefice, whileſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my thus nouriſheth Vipers to eat their way through our Mothers Bowels— (God
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100259:19"/>
knows my heart) I abhominate a private deſign when I thus ſpeak, as much as a moderation againſt the Rules of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I petition for a poorer ſort of Brethren than my ſelf, for the Prieſt unbeneficed, who is Ingenuous and Open-ſpirited, Generous and Devout, and a Lover of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> And would not the primitive Canons of this Church be rather more than leſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; If ſuch an incarnate <hi>Seraphin</hi> had always the next Living of value in the Churches own gift. If Self-intereſt ſhould ever creep into a Cathedral, it will firſt pull down the Honour, and then the Walls. It is not certainly for the peace or ſafety of our holy Mother, that any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, Conſcientious, Learned Prieſt ſhould ſpend his time in a diſcontented Contemplation of his misfortunes, whileſt a barbarous Nonconformity without, and Moderation within are ſuſtained with a full and free enjoyment of all Creature-comforts, in order to the ruining of the beſt of Churches. This is, I hope, a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable digreſſion, as conſonant with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100259:20"/>
the Text, and not repugnant to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in the Caſe before us, as tending to increaſe and ſupport the very little flock, God knows, of the truely zealous for our (no leſs Ancient than Orderly) Conſtitutions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi>—To this Power of Eccleſiaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ical Superiours we have the harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſſent alſo of all Reformed Churches. Thete are two Excellent Books of Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> entitled, <hi>Eccleſiae Anglicanae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus ſchiſmaticorum criminationes vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciae,</hi> and <hi>The Church of England not condemned by any other Reformed Churches;</hi> both ſo well known to this Audience, as ſufficiently ſatisfactory in this Particular to all intelligent and unbiaſt perſons, that they ſpare me the Labour of any farther Diſcourſe: And indeed our Mother, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is ſo far Juſtified againſt all imaginable ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Oppoſers, from the publiquely-printed harmony of Confeſſions (in which book are inſerted alſo the Thirty nine Articles) and by the publick open practice of our neighbour-nations (we not condemning
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100259:20"/>
them nor they us) that our enemies have recourſe to Clamour and Noiſe, and want only an opportunity by Swords and Piſtols to encounter our Reaſons and Demonſtrations; Club-Law muſt once again gain that advantage (when occaſion offers) which they deſpair of by Arguments and Diſputations.</p>
            <p>They are not for treating like Men, but fighting like Beaſts; Men neither to be broke nor to be ſoftned, all Anvil and Adamant; and Nonconformiſts in all other Kingdoms, and over all the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World, as well as to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (as is admirably proved by the Learned Author aforeſaid). All the Reformed Churches maintain this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, That every National Church hath Power to make Laws for herſelf in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, not expreſly commanded or forbidden in the Word, and that they may vary according to Times, Places and Perſons, and other Circumſtances; and not one of them but hath acted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Principle in making Laws
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100259:21"/>
different from their Neighbour Churches. I therefore paſs to the laſt Particular (not only Scriptures, Reaſon, Experience, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Councils and Reformed Churches) but our Nonconformiſts and very Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by their Confeſſions and Practices, own this Power in Eccleſiaſtical Superiors, however refractory to our preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions.</p>
            <p>And firſt I cite <hi>Calamy,</hi> in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-Sermon; who tells us, That the Covenant is to be taken ſtanding, the head uncovered, and the right hand bare muſt be lift up, which are emphatical Cermonies (ſayeth the Man of God,) and Significant that we call God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp;c. Here I note that there are as many Cermonies in this unlawful Oath as the Church of <hi>England,</hi> hath in her whole Worſhip legally authorized, and the Ceremonies are ſignificant too, as well as ours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I cite the preface to the Directory, where the thorough-Reformers thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude: <hi>We are reſolved to lay aſide the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100259:21"/>
Common prayer-book and ſet up the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtead thereof; where we hold forth what is of Divine Inſtitution in every Ordinance, and other things (not of Divine Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) we do hold forth according to the Rules of Chriſtian prudence conſonant with the general Canons of the Word of God?</hi> But now I demand, By what Law of God or Man have you the Sole Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg of thus holding forth? Why may not the Church of <hi>England</hi> uſe the ſame liberty of her Chriſtian prudence, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Rules of the Word? <hi>dic Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliane colorem.</hi> If this Priviledg be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a Directory, without Law ſet up, why not to a Liturgy, legally eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? and if granted, the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> hath thus proceeded in the Liturgy preſcribed <hi>viz.</hi> by Chriſtian prudence, and the Canons of the Word.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I cite a (not unlearned-Treatiſe of the Presbyterian entitled, <hi>An Alarum by way of anſwer to the laſt warning-peice,</hi> where the Authors tell us, <hi>That no Man endued with right Reaſon, but will ſay
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100259:22"/>
there is a neceſſity of a Government; if of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, then of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, elſe it will be confuſed: therefore there is a neceſſity that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhould obſerve ſuch Orders, Time, Place, and Geſtures, as the Parliament and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> (but why not as the King, Biſhops and Clergy?) <hi>ſhall appoint;</hi> Very ſound and good. (It follows) <hi>No man that hath any uſe of Conſcience in any thing, but he will acknowledg that he is bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to obey the Laws of the Land in things indifferent, and deſerves Cenſure for being turbulent even in matters of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:</hi> But now the Caſe is altered, the Nonconformiſts being not in Throne of Government, it is falſe Doctrine at preſent in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. I cite Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who (writing to his Brethren <hi>Brandon</hi> and <hi>Caryl</hi>) cleaves a hair, <hi>Let me be bold to tell my Brethren of the Miniſtry, That (though</hi> I <hi>deny them to have any Authority againſt the Word) yet ſo great is their Authority as Guides and Governors of the Church, in things agreeable to, and but generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100259:22"/>
in the Word, that the want of the knowledg of this Truth hath been the occaſion of all the Schiſms and Confuſions in</hi> England; <hi>And till we have taught even our godly people, what Obedience is due to there ſpiritual Guides, the Church of</hi> England <hi>will never have any good or eſtabliſhed Order: I ſay again, we are broken for want of the knowledg of this Truth, and till it be better known we ſhall never be bound up and healed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which if you add the formal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of the Brethren of <hi>New England</hi> for admiſſion of Members, even theſe precious Saints will condemn themſelves, or muſt juſtify this beſt of Reformed Churches. Thus I have by Scripture, Reaſon, Experience, Fathers Councils, Reformed Churches, and the Confeſſions and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Nonconformiſts themſelves, plainly proved a Power in Church-gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to make Canons, and decree Rites for the external Solemnity and <hi>Decorum,</hi> and Order of Divine Service; to which all Prieſts and People are to yeild Obedience
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100259:23"/>
under their Government and Juriſdiction— <hi>quod erat demonſtrandum.</hi> From the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Diſcourſe I do (as a zealous Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) reprove my Brethren of moderate Principles, as Commentators, as Caſuiſts and as pretenders to the Politicks; And ſo with a brief Exhortation to all my reverend Brethren, ſhall conclude the Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are abominable Commentators. They ſhall always ſign the Infant bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with the Croſs, (that is to ſay) the Children of Conformiſts; but the Canon ſays not it muſt be done to the Seed of the righteous: Not marry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Banes or Licence at uncanonical Hours or prohibited times, or without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of their Parents or Governors (that is); The Miniſter ſhall not do it <hi>gratis,</hi> but if ſoundly payd it is no Diſobedience againſt the Canon of the Church. He ſhall not diminiſh the Prayers of the Church on the account of Preaching or any other reſpect (that is to ſay) unleſs it be to increaſe the Salary, or to lengthen the Sermon, for to make way for the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100259:23"/>
freely conceived, Directory-way of canting in the Pulpit. He ſhall read the Letany on Wedneſdays and Fridays every week; <hi>Antiphraſis voces tibi per contraria ſignat.</hi>- Canonical Obedience, <hi>in omnibus licitis et honeſtis,</hi> that is, as far as the new Saints will permit, upon whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend for a Maintenance: The confirming their Doctrins by Scripture according to Expoſition of the Fathers, and their Mothers own Articles; <hi>Populo ut placerent quas feciſſent fabulas:</hi> Whenſoever they officiate, to wear the Surplice (that is) if their precious Benefactors do not account the Garment Popiſh, and take occaſion hence to withdraw the Creature-comforts: Not give the Sacrament to any men but ſuch as kneel (that is) if the poſture be approved by ſuch as have Communion with the Lord Jeſus in the pureſt Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. To bid Prayer before Sermon is to pray by the Spirit; and as breiſly as conveniently we may, is more or leſs, half an hour or a full glaſs, according to the Judgment or contribution of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100259:24"/>
Saints. The Sick ſhall be prayed for by the Form at the Viſitation preſcribed (that is) the Pariſh-clark ſhall keep the Tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et till the Soul-ſearcher is in the Pulpit: The ſame Form to be uſed in private, unleſs the Schiſmatick puts his hand in his pocket and makes a Preſent, and then the caſe is altered, and the Law not violated. No Man vows Poverty when he ſwears to obey the Biſhop: But the Man of God can ſometimes ſupererogate; He ſhall preach one Sermon every Lords day (that is to ſay) two at the leaſt; He ſhall uſe Catechizing in the afternoon (that is) if the people <hi>(et vox populi, vox Dei)</hi> had not much rather have a Sermon: And the Desk is unhallowed; It is no Sermon neither, unleſs it come from the holy Mount: After all, we muſt have a ſtrain of <hi>Sternhold</hi> and <hi>Hopkins</hi> after Sermons for our godly ſolace, while precious the Man cons over the Heads of the foregoing Diſcourſe; a way of ſinging and canting which hath neither Law of the Land nor Canon of a Synod to juſtify its uſe,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100259:24"/>
nor any Approbation (upon Record, either of Civil or Eccleſiaſtical Superiors; but the people love to have it ſo: By this craft theſe Men of God have their wealth, and this ſhall be obſerved (not required) above all the Churches ancient and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conſtitutions; thus precious Man Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines for Money, and the ſmall Levite for handfuls of Barley, and pieces of Bread; and turns Spiritual Pedlar to avoid the Statutes of Vagrants, and both ſells the Church for a Subſiſtence, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels againſt the orderly Laws and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We will conſider him as a Caſuiſt likewiſe, and then the Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor will appear to be leſs ridiculous. With our Brother-Conformiſts of moderate O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, to comply with a Faction againſt the Church and the Laws, for a benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, is to be a Jew with Jews, and a Gentile with Gentiles, and being crafty to take their Money; then they catch the People with guile (as the Apoſtle did in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100259:25"/>
the converſition of Souls (admirable Caſuiſts) who cannot (or will not) reconcile St. <hi>Pauls</hi> two Sentences; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming all things to all men,</hi> and <hi>if I yet pleaſe men, I ſhould not be the Servant of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> the beſt Salvo they have is a late Act of Parliament (which being duely executed) It did appear there was no difference between the Purſes and the Conſciences of Nonconformiſts; rather than loſe an Office of profit, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience was ſatisfied, that he could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with the Church, and kneel at the Euchariſt, and was not defiled with the company of Sinners at the holy Ordinance: So that he that gains the Purſe gains the Soul of our precious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters; (a uſe of Conſolation to our moderate Caſuiſts). But if this doth not help them, they are certainly loſt to all intents and purpoſes. It muſt not be, <hi>Paul a ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe): If ſuch imitate that zealous Apoſtle who (by omiſſion of known Miniſterial Duties) have forfeited the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100259:25"/>
Faith of a Prieſt, and the Feaſt of a good Conſcience, who ſubſcribe with their hands and ſomething beſides (which <hi>ex animo</hi> ſignifies in ſome approved Dictionaries) and yet Pope Intereſt is ſupream over Kings and Biſhops, and can diſpence with all imaginable engagements to Eccleſiaſtical Superiors and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For Sixty years and upwards our preſent Canons have been obligatory upon us, but theſe Caſuiſts can tell you that a Cuſtom of Five or Six years (If it let in the Evangelical Graces of profit and eaſe) can preſcribe againſt the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom aforeſaid, and every offender againſt this New Law, muſt be called a Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Conformiſt to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> But I humbly conceive (with ſubmiſſion to better Judgments) that for a Prieſt (after Subſcription) neither to obey the Churches Laws, nor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of others, to ſerve upon his holy Mother all his ſordid and degenerous ends, and keep open her bleeding Wounds for his own advantage, and to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100259:26"/>
turn Renegadoe (as a Souldier for pay flies to the Tents of Enemies) is a Crime that doubles its malignity from the Quality of the Actor, and (if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) we want a number above the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, to expreſs ſo complicated a wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I do as little underſtand the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of theſe men, as their Caſuiſtical Divinity, or barbarous Commentaries; what they call a prudential Compliance, is only the want of Courage and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; their Moderation is an open defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to that Heroical integrity which ſhould ſpeak the Prieſt a Saint and a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman. It is with theſe men (as <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Fabius Valens</hi> Captain to <hi>Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leius) utrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilium aſpernatus eſt, &amp; quod inter ancipitia deterrimum eſt, nec providit;</hi> It is ſo with theſe partial Conformiſts, they have not Courage enough to embark heartily on one ſide, nor Providence enough to eſcape the hatred of both. It were more politick to take the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100259:26"/>
advice of <hi>Suetonius, Quando non efficias quin alterum habiturus ſis inimicum aut ſocium, Jacienda tunc eſt alea alterutri adhaerendum eſt:</hi> Let them be either tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Conformiſts or Non-conformiſts, the middle moderate practice is attended on with an Epiſcopal Rod executing the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non againſt Revolters, and an angry God, who (as he hateth robbery for burnt-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings) ſo he abhors the Prieſt that curtails the Sacrifice of Obedience: Nay to add more torment to their lives, there is a Sacrilegious Layman, who believes in his Conſcience he may as well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Titles, as the Prieſt the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: Wilt thou ſue him in the Court of the Biſhop, whoſe Orders thou doſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe? Wilt thou fly to that Law in thy neceſſity, to which in point of Duty thou haſt denyed thy homage? When the ſame Law puts thy Bread into thy mouth, and the Common-prayer-book into thy hand, Wilt thou Read the Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy in the way of Moderation, and take the Lay-man by the Throat for the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100259:27"/>
uttermoſt farthing? Haſt thou Confidence enough to accuſe him of Sacriledg before the Right Reverend <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> when <hi>Clodius accuſat maechos, Catilina Cethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things duly conſidered, ſuffer I beſeech you my reverend Brethren, The Word of Exhortation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is taken for granted, that the reading of Divine Service as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; If firſt beſeech you therefore to read this Worſhip with all imaginable Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reverence; let us be a ſort of incarnate Seraphins when we offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate by the Liturgy in the holy Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: thus we ſhall ſilence the calumny (equally uncharitable and ridiculous) of the Presbyterian Divines, who (in their grand debates) briskly tell us, that an able and holy Miniſtry flows immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from Pulpit-conceptions, according to the variety of Subjects and occaſions, and that Men are apt to loſe a great
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100259:27"/>
deal of affection by the conſtant uſe of the ſame Forms; let us (with the bleſſed Jeſus) pray earneſtly, uſing the ſame Words; be truly zealous at the Prayers of our Church, and demonſtrate that inward fervour by the Text <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and we ſhall ſilence theſe inſipid vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious Canters, who place all their Religion in their rude impremeditated and tumultuary effuſions. The reverend Doctor <hi>Fell</hi> in his life of Doctor <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> obſerves of that Divine (the late glory of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) that his tranſport at his Prayer threw him ſometimes proſtrate on the earth, that his tears would interrupt his Words in the Common Service of the Church; let theſe men know that revile Liturgy, by our following this eminent Prieſt in holy fervors, that the Votary (not the Prayer) is in fault, when ever zeal is wanting at the publick Devotions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With Submiſſion to better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Canons relating to Divine
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100259:28"/>
Service would be more carefully obſerved amongſt us, if in Cities, Corporations and the moſt Populous places, the Ten-pound-Man did not read the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>I therefore requeſt that the Searcher, Melter and Eſtabliſher of Souls, may read the Prayers of the Church, and that he may not be permitted in the leaſt to curtail the ſolemn Worſhip for his own private conceptions; and then the People will begin to conſider, with themſelves, whether God do not require ſomething elſe beſides Ears and Elbows in the Congregation of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I do humbly Requeſt that all that Preach Twice every Sunday and forget Catechiſing, that they would once more Read the Fourty ſive Canon, and Fifty ninth Conſtitution: I muſt and do open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſs that I underſtand not the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Tongue, if two Sermons every Lords
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100259:28"/>
Day be equally Canonical with this Duty of Inſtructing the younger ſort in the Churches Catechiſm, in order to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That I may not be miſconſtrued as Enemy to Preaching, I do freely conſent from my heart that every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter with Cure of Souls do herein conſult his own prudence: I ſhall not contend whether once or twice, but I preſume the former to be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but let the Clergy Preach e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day of the week provided the old Canon be obſerved, That every— Preacher in this Province take a ſpecial care that they Teach or Deliver no other Doctrines than what is conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Word of God, and Collected thence by the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and godly Biſhops. Unleſs this ancient good wholeſom Rule be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully put in practice, the Church will be more edified by our Silence than our Sermons.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:100259:29"/>5. What if the Feaſts and Faſts and Letany-days of the Church were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically, and Conſcientiouſly obſerved, amongſt us, It would infinitely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote true Piety, the Churches Peace; and I know no pretence againſt it, but Pride and Intereſt, Applauſe and Benevolence, which too frequently can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel all our Vows and Obligations.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let us think the Nation and Church wiſer than a particular Prieſt, and the Liturgy more weighty than our own Pulpit effuſions; and confine our ſelves to the Canonical way of bidding Prayers with that brevity that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non-prayer mentions (God is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the Novelty of our expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) but poſſibly the People is the Idol to which we ſacrifice, and from whom we expect an anſwer to our petitions; and then there is ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for a long-winded Cant before the Pulpit-Diſcourſe, becauſe the rabble do admire what is equally ridiculous with themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:100259:29"/>Laſtly, The Seventy fifth Canon muſt never be forgotten, enjoyning a Regular Life and Converſation; and this joyned, with a publick Spirit that abominates a compliance againſt the Rules of Conſcience and Honour, is abſolutely requiſite to <hi>the doing all things decently and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
